All right, let's talk about the causes
of that massive economic boom in the
1950s and how it contributed to metric
butt-loads of migration. So, if you're
ready to get them brain cows milked,
let's get to it. Okay, so in the years
after World War II, the United States
economy went positively nuts, and there
were basically two reasons for that
you're going to need to know. First of
all, a burgeoning private sector
contributed to economic growth. So,
recall that during the war, two economic
realities were occurring at the same
time. One, the nation's industrial
infrastructure was focused heavily on
the production of munitions for the war
instead of on the production of consumer
goods. And that's because it turns out
it's easier to win a war by dropping
bombs and throwing consumer-grade
toasters at them. But then two, the war
effort required the government to
introduce rationing programs that
limited food and services to consumers
in order to keep supplies flowing to the
troops across the globe. And so, you put
those two ingredients in a pot and baby,
you got a stew going. And here's what
that stew tastes like. Since Americans
had very little opportunity to purchase
consumer goods on a mass scale during
the war, they saved a record amount of
their disposable income either in banks
or by purchasing war bonds. And so, when
the war was over, that fat stack of cash
buzzing with potential energy all of a
sudden converted into kinetic energy as
Americans spent money on mass-produced
consumer goods. And arguably, the
widespread adoption of the automobile
represented the most significant example
of increased consumer spending. So,
after World War II, pent-up consumer
demand led to a significant spike in the
production of consumer cars from
companies like Ford and General Motors,
which demonstrated the shift from a
wartime manufacturing economy to a
consumer economy. Oh, and by the way, if
you want no guys to follow along with
this video and all my videos, you can
check that link in the description.
Anyway, you didn't think all this
economic growth is owing only to
Americans who had saved money, did you?
Don't be crazy. No, credit cards were
also widely adopted in the 1950s and
1960s, which allowed consumers to
purchase goods and services without cash
on the condition that they pay their
balance each month including a small
interest fee for the privilege. And the
first widespread adoption of the credit
card was the Diners Club card, which
originated in New York City and was a
way to pay for food at restaurants, but
soon expanded to include other services
as well. And soon thereafter, Visa and
MasterCard offered competing options for
buying on credit, all of which increased
consumer spending significantly. But
then the second cause of this fantastic
economic growth was significant spending
from the federal government. So
remember, we're in the 1950s, and that
means the Cold War is getting frostier
by the minute, and so in order to keep
those filthy Soviet communists from
spreading, Big Daddy Government reached
real deep into his pocket. For example,
in 1944, Congress passed the GI Bill,
which offered financial assistance to
veterans returning home from World War
II. And they used those funds to pay for
college and to secure home loans at very
low interest rates, which in turn
contributed to the growth of the
suburban home industry, of which I shall
have more to say in a moment. But then
in 1956, under the administration of
Dwight D. Eisenhower, Congress passed
the Federal Aid Highway Act, which
funded the construction of thousands of
miles of interstate highways. And
Congress didn't just throw money at
highway construction for funsies. No,
again, we're in the Cold War, and
therefore the construction of interstate
highways was deemed in large part a
military necessity for quick
mobilization of military assets across
the country. But anyway, the
construction of all those highways had
two major effects. First of all, the
government infusion of billions of
dollars into the private sector led to
the growth and increased productivity of
several industries needed for highway
construction, like the steel, oil, and
construction industries. Second, by
connecting urban centers to suburban
housing developments, these highways
spurred the growth of the suburbs and a
further dependence on automobiles. And
third, this new highway system further
connected regional markets and allowed
manufacturing operations to easily
spread to new areas, most notably the
South. And all that combined just kept
the economy cranking like a boss. But
government spending also contributed to
the growth of the economy by granting
contracts to private companies related
to the defense industry. Again, it's the
Cold War, and a major feature of that
conflict was an arms race between the US
and the Soviets, and that means lots of
government spending. Now, a good example
of this kind of spending was the growth
of the high-tech industry in Silicon
Valley, which specialized in the
creation of early computer systems that
were mainly used by the US military. And
look, the origin stories of many of
these companies, like Apple or IBM,
often promoted the rugged and slapdash
genius founders who exemplified the
American dream by building their
computers and their companies out of
their garages. And look, while that was
true, it was equally true that the
high-tech industry owed much of its
growth and contribution to the economy
to the deep pockets of Big Daddy
Government. Okay, so those are two of
the main causes for the economic
prosperity of the post-war years, and
now I reckon you're itching to hear
about some of the effects, and I'm going
to give you three. First of all, along
with the general prosperity, also came a
rapid increase in population from the
mid-40s to the mid-60s, a phenomenon
that became known as the baby boom. And
here's where I tell you that it's a
general law of most of world history
that more money equals more babies. So,
when the Great Depression hit, the
economic instability caused the US birth
rate to plummet. However, the growth of
the economy and rising wages in the
post-war years meant that families could
more easily support multiple children.
Additionally, the development of and
access to new vaccinations against
diseases like diphtheria and polio meant
that more babies survived childhood and
thus contributed to the expansion of the
population. And then, the second effect
of economic growth was a phenomenon
known as suburbanization, which
describes a mass migration of
middle-class families to the suburbs.
And the best example I can give you here
is the success of Levittown in Long
Island, New York. So, our boy William
Levitt applied the principles of Henry
Ford's perfection of the assembly line
to the mass production of single-family
suburban homes. And his first major
project was the creation of Levittown,
which consisted of about 17,000 suburban
homes. So, Levitt was able to streamline
the home construction process down to 26
individual steps, with workers moving
from one home site to another,
performing only a single step for each
home, which was very Fordish of him. And
as it did with automobiles, the mass
production of homes drove the prices
down significantly, and enabled
middle-class nuclear families to afford
a house built on a small plot of land.
And no small amount of those migrating
families bought those homes with loans
that came from the GI Bill. But then,
once all those homes were built,
families spent lots of money on
furniture and the latest home appliances
like refrigerators and washing machines
and cars to get to and from work, thus
jamming the economy into an even higher
gear. However, it's important to note
that the growth of suburbia was largely
a middle-class white phenomenon. For
example, William Levitt, with support
from the Federal Housing Administration,
refused to sell homes in his
neighborhoods to black families. In
fact, one significant reason white
families moved out of New York City to
Long Island was to distance themselves
from the explosive growth of the black
population that arrived during the Great
Migration. And this kind of housing
segregation was only further enforced by
the practice of redlining in which banks
marked high-risk urban areas on maps and
then refused to lend money to people
wanted to buy homes or obtain home
improvement loans in those
neighborhoods. And these inner-city
neighborhoods were populated with
low-income minorities, often black
people. And since many of the mostly
white suburban communities had covenants
that prevented minorities from buying
houses there, people in redlined
districts had little choice but to
remain where they were. But because they
were unable to obtain loans, their
housing structures fell into greater and
greater disrepair. And then the third
big effect of the post-war prosperity
was a massive movement of Americans that
became known as the Sunbelt Migration.
So, this right here is what we call the
Sunbelt. And of special importance to
this migration was California, Florida,
and Texas. And why, says you, did so
many Americans move to these places?
Well, says I, there were essentially
three reasons. First, Americans from the
Northeast and Midwest were apparently
tired of the butt-cold winters where
they lived and were thus attracted to
these states because of their warm
climates. And because new technologies
like air conditioners made the summer
heat more comfortable, Americans flocked
to suburban homes in which this kind of
technology came standard. Second,
Americans moved because of increased
mobility. And here it was the federal
expansion of the Interstate Highway
System and the widespread adoption of
automobiles that made it possible for so
many Americans to move across regions
with relative ease. And then third, much
of the federal government spending on
the defense industry was concentrated in
these states and that spending created
millions of jobs that attracted migrants
from the north and Midwest. Now, here's
where I tell you that one of the main
effects of this migration was to
redistribute political and economic
power away from the Northeast and
Midwest and into the Sunbelt states. For
example, since the number of seats in
the House of Representatives is
apportioned by population, the Sunbelt
migration significantly shifted the
distribution of power in the House
toward the Sunbelt. In fact, by 1972,
the Sunbelt states now had more
electoral votes than Northeastern and
Midwestern states combined. And that had
the effect of strengthening certain
political coalitions, like for example,
the Dixiecrats, which is a group of
Southern and who majored in policies
upholding racial segregation in the
South. And their growing influence was
bolstered by the rise of a new
conservatism that was shared by many
white middle-class suburbanites who had
moved during the Sunbelt migration since
they focused heavily on states' rights
and upholding white racial superiority.
And that's going to have some serious
consequences when we get to the Civil
Rights Movement, but alas, that topic
has its very own video, so I'll leave it
there for now. Well, all right, you can
click here to watch my other Unit 8
videos, or you can click here to grab my
video note guides, which are going to
help you get all the contents of this
course firmly crammed into your brain
folds. And I'm glad you came around, and
I'll catch you on the flip-flop. I'm Mr.
Bett.